The conflict between Li and Wei has become chaotic.
李太傅と魏丞相の争いは すでに乱局となっています
And you intend to establish your own faction in the future.
これから侯爺は ご独立をなさるつもりですか
Do you wish to make this chaos even worse?
この乱局を さらにかき乱すおつもりですか
As a man,
男たるもの
one must not be a fence-sitter.
他人の妻に手を出すべかず
As a minister,
臣子たるもの
one must not switch sides frivolously.
二君に仕えるべからず
That is all I have to say.
言いたいことは以上だ
Zheng! Zheng!
義兄さん
Are you here?
ここにいるの
Zheng, Mrs. Zhao asked you to go back for lunch.
叔母さんが昼食の時だと言った
Young lady, why don't you come in and sit for a while?
お嬢さん 中に入って休まないのか
I'm not going into a villain's house.
ううん 大悪党の家には 入らないわ
Thank you, Mr. Scholar.
ありがとう 書生大人
Why do you call me Mr. Scholar?
なぜ私を「書生大人」と呼んでる？
My sister said your carriage was full of books.
お姉ちゃんが言ってたの 馬車の中が本でいっぱいだって
I won't disturb your rest, My Lord.
では お邪魔しないぞ
Please pretend I was never here.
私がなかったことに
Let's go.
行こう
Was that man really the Marquis of Wu'an?
この人が本当に武安侯なのか
He just broke a cup. So what?
杯が割れただけでしょ
The Marquis of Wu'an is nothing special.
武安侯も大したことないようです
His skills seem to have been improving.
彼の腕はますます上がっているな
[Pursuit of Jade]
[逐玉]
[Episode 11]
[第11話]
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[樊記煮込み屋]
Changyu!
長玉
Qianqian?
浅姉さん
Which young lady has been doing dirty, exhausting work all day
どこのお嬢さんが 一日中汚い力仕事をしたけど
yet is still this pretty?
相変わらずこんなにきれいなの？
Hop on. I'll take you home.
乗って 家まで送るわ
No need. I'll go back myself.
いいえ 自分で帰ります
Usually, I'd let you be,
いつもは好きにさせてるけど
but today I kept you here late
今日は宴会が多すぎて
because there were too many banquets.
残ってもらったんだわ
It's already dark.
もう暗くなったし
I'm worried about you walking alone at night.
あなた一人で夜道を 歩かせるのは心配よ
Get in.
乗りなさい
It's okay. I can manage it alone. You go.
大丈夫 私一人でも できますから 行って
Well then, thank you.
じゃあ お願いします
[Fan's Braised Meat Shop]
[樊記煮込み屋]
Come out.
出てこい
Your Lordship.
侯爺
[Xie Wu, Blood-Robed Cavalry Guard] [Xie Qi, Blood-Robed Cavalry Guard]
[血衣騎親衛隊 謝五] [血衣騎親衛隊 謝七]
Your Lordship,
侯爺
we are late.
遅参いたしました
You may rise.
上がれ
How many of you came?
何人で来たのか
Just Xie Qi and me.
私と謝七だけです
We were afraid of being noticed,
見張られている恐れが ありますので
so we didn't bring the other guards along.
他の護衛は連れておりません
Your Lordship, fortunately you are safe.
侯爺 ご無事で何よりです
Unfortunately, Xie Yi and Xie San
残念ながら謝一と謝三は
died because of me.
私のせいで犠牲になった
We brothers once swore
我らは誓ったことがあります
to keep you safe
侯爺の無事を守るためなら
even at the cost of our lives.
死んでも悔いはありません
No one from the Xie family
我が謝家の者は
would die in vain.
決して犬死になってはならない
All of us are hoping you return soon.
侯爺が一日も早く お戻りになるのを待っています
That Wei Xuan is running rampant in the army.
魏宣のやつは 軍隊でやりたい放題です
He flaunts his power every day.
やつは毎日軍で威張り散らし
The brothers can hardly wait to tie him up
皆 やつを縛り上げて
and throw him to the wolves.
狼の餌に してやりたくてたまりません
Let him be.
好きにさせておけ
Before long, a bloody battle
この先は
between us and Prince Changxin in Chongzhou is inevitable.
崇州長信王との血戦は避けられない
Storing grain is the top priority right now.
今は兵糧の備蓄が一番重要だ
The Court refuses to release grain.
朝廷は兵糧を支給せず
Wei Xuan has accepted Prime Minister Wei's military order
魏宣は魏丞相の軍令を受け
and plans to requisition grain locally.
現地で徴収するつもりのようだ
Sixteen years ago,
十六年前
it was in Jinzhou where the Xie Army
謝家軍は瑾州で
suffered a crushing defeat due to lack of provisions and support.
兵糧の補給が届かなかったため 惨敗した
I absolutely cannot repeat the same mistake.
決して二の舞は踏んではならん
Wei Xuan is ambitious for great achievements.
魏宣は功を焦る男で
It's only a matter of time before he loses to Prince Changxin.
長信王に敗れるのも 時間の問題だろう
Let's just go with the flow
いっそこの流れに乗り
and let Wei Xuan and those idiots under his command
魏宣に配下の無能どもを率いさせ
serve as bait
おとりにさせろ
to lure Prince Changxin to lead troops south.
長信王を南下させれば
By then, I will have my own strategy.
その時は私が対応できる
So, Your Lordship, you don't plan to return to camp for now?
では侯爺はしばらく陣営に 戻られないというつもりですか
You go back first
お前たちは先に戻れ
and spread the news of my death.
私が死んだという 知らせを広めてくれ
The more people know, the better.
知る者が多ければ多いほどいい
Yes.
はっ
Go now.
行け
The braised pork is sold out today.
今日の煮込み肉は 全部売り切れましたわ
The pig head meat was very popular.
豚頭肉がすごく人気だったんですよ
Really?
本当？
A few days ago, Mrs. Wang said her daughter is getting married
この間王お婆さんが 娘さんの嫁入りで
and ordered half a side of pork from me.
豚半身を注文してくれたんです
Won't that mean more work for you?
また大変になるわね
I welcome this kind of work.
こういう苦労なら大歓迎ですよ
Who is it? Who are you?
誰だ お前たちは？
I'll go out and take a look.
私が見てきます
Qianqian, don't come out now.
浅姉さん　外に出ないでね
I'll deal with them.
こいつらは私に任せて
Beat her.
やっちまえ
Who sent you?
誰に頼まれたの？
Was it him?
あの人でしょう？
Why won't he let me go after all these years?
何年もたったのに なぜ私を放っておいてくれないの？
Help! Help!
誰か 助けて
Changyu, watch out!
長玉 気をつけて
Don't run!
逃げるな
This voice sounds familiar.
この声 なんとなく聞き覚えがあるけど
Butcher Guo.
郭豚屠り
Mrs. Fan...
樊お嬢さん
Heroine Fan.
樊侠女
Mommy!
母さん！
I just lost my mind for a moment.
ただの出来心だけだ
You've gone against me time and again.
何度も私を敵に回して
That doesn't look like losing your mind for a moment.
出来心だけとは思えないけど
Someone paid us
誰かに金で雇われたんだ
to kill you.
あんたを殺せって
Who?
誰だ
Who!
誰って！
Changyu!
長玉
Since we're selling one,
一人を売るのも
we might as well sell two!
二人を売るのも同じだ
Go to hell!
死ね
Bastard! Come at me if you have the guts!
この野郎 何があったら私を相手にして
I'll come at you then!
望みどおりにしてやる
Changyu!
長玉
I...
俺…
Changyu! Changyu?
長玉　長玉
Are you okay?
大丈夫？
[Xigu Lane]
[西固巷]
Yan Zheng, did you see Changyu?
言正 長玉に会ったのか
What's happening here?
一体どうしたんだ？
-She was drugged. Go get some water. -Okay.
- 酔薬にかかられた　冷水を持って来い - わかった
Honey, come help.
あなた 早く手伝って
Hello, sir. Hello, sir.
こんばんは　叔父さん
What's happening here?
どういうことだ？
What?
何？
My butt... hurts.
尻が…痛い
Hurts?
痛いのか
Where does it hurt?
どこが痛い？
My butt!
尻だ
Your butt what?
尻がどうした？
My butt hurts!
尻が痛い
Why hasn't the pain killed you?
痛みで死んでも惜しくないぞ
Despicable man!
卑劣なやつ
Please spare me.
好漢　勘弁して
I'm not a bandit from Qingfeng Stronghold.
俺は清風寨の山賊じゃない
I was bullied by those two broads—
溢香楼であの女たちに…
no—
いや
those two ladies from Yixiang Restaurant.
この二人の姉さんに虐められたたら
I just wanted to scare them.
彼女に驚かしたかっただけさ
Guo!
このクズ
You took your grudge against Fan Erniu
樊二牛との仇を
out on this poor orphan girl?
哀れな孤児にぶつけたなんて
Are you even human?
それでも人間と言えるの？
My butt...
尻　尻が...
Say no more.
少し黙ってくれ
Do you think the fire isn't big enough?
これ以上騒ぎを大きくしたいのか
Do you want to blow the roof off?
屋根を吹っ飛ばす気か
It hurts!
痛い 痛っ
Just to scare them?
脅しか
Didn't you drug her?
酔薬をかけただろ
What exactly did you want?
一体何をしたいんだ？
I wanted to knock them out first...
まず酔薬で気絶させて
And then?
それから？
Speak!
言え
Then destroy her meridians...
彼女の経絡を断って
Is that all?
それだけ？
And sell her to the mountains...
山の奥に売るんだ
Stop!
やめろ
Yan, doing this
言兄がこんなことしても
will only dirty your hands.
自分の手が汚れるだけだ
How he should be punished
どう裁くか
is for the authorities to decide.
役所による決めるべきだ
The authorities? If I hadn't been here today,
役所？ 今日は私がいなければ
something bad would have happened to Changyu.
長玉はとっくに 危ない目にあっただろ
If you accept your fate, who can save you?
自分まで諦めたら 誰も救えないぞ
I will take
私の恨みは
my own revenge!
私が晴らす
Stop!
やめろ
No!
駄目だ
Yan Zheng!
言正
Don't kill him.
殺さないで
It's not worth it.
そうする価値がないわ
Are you okay?
大丈夫？
Lie down.
横になれ
Rest assured and sleep.
安心して寝よう
I won't kill him.
殺しはしない
Alright, don't cry.
よしよし もう泣かないで
I have plenty of strength.
お姉ちゃんは力がいっぱいあるわ
Look.
ほら
My hands are fine,
手も足も
and my feet are fine too.
ちゃんとしてるじゃない
Stop crying.
もう泣かないで
Changyu...
お姉ちゃん
Help me get a basin of warm water, okay?
お姉ちゃんに お湯をくんできてくれる？
Okay.
うん
How is it? Does your head still hurt?
どうだ？ 頭はまだ痛むのか
Do you feel uncomfortable anywhere else?
他にどこか悪いところはある？
If you had killed someone for me
私のために人を殺して
and gone to prison,
牢屋にでも入ったら
my head would really hurt.
それこそつらいわ
Promise me.
約束して
Don't get into trouble.
無事でいて
Don't worry.
安心しろ
I'll be fine.
私は大丈夫だ
Manager, the doors and windows are locked.
店主 戸締りは済みました
The water vats for fire are full.
火消し用の水鉢も満タンです
And I've assigned the boys
配下どもにも
to take shifts to guard every two hours.
二時間交代で見張りをさせています
Do you have any other orders?
他にご用はありますか
Manager, is there going to be a war?
店主 戦でも始まるんですか
Add 2 more locks tomorrow.
明日 鍵を二つ増やして
There are already 3 locks on 2 doors.
すでに二重扉に三重の鍵ですよ
You still want to add more?
まだ増やしますか？
Yes.
ええ
Add one more layer,
もう一つ増やして
and reinforce the door frames with iron.
扉の縁も鉄枠で 補強してちょうだい
Okay.
わかりました
Mom.
お母さん
Were you good today, Bao'er?
宝児 今日はいい子だった？
Very good.
すごくいい子だったよ
I didn't go out at all.
外にも出なかったよ
I finished all the homework you left for me.
お母さんが出した宿題も 全部終えたわ
Such a good boy?
本当にいい子だね
Let's be this good tomorrow too, okay?
じゃあ明日もいい子になってね
[Luyuan]
[麓原]
Great move!
見事な一手だな
Great...
素晴らしい
An Xu, so you know how to play Go?
安旭も囲碁ができるとは
Just a little.
すこしだけです
How about playing a round with me?
では私と一局してどう？
Sure.
はい
That was satisfying!
痛快だった
Let's play another round tomorrow.
明日また一局やろう
Okay.
いいですよ
Headmaster.
学長
When I was young, I read a fragment of a Go manual
私は幼い頃 ある棋譜の断簡を 読んだことがあります
called "The Mystery of Qi."
書名は「気蘊玄機」と言います
I heard that your Library has over 10,000 books.
ここの御書楼には一万冊以上の 蔵書があると聞いて
I wanted to find it,
探してみたんですが
but I haven't been able to yet.
見つからなかったんです
This book
その本は
is indeed not in the Library.
確かに御書楼にはない
However,
でも
in the Gongsun family's collection,
公孫の家での蔵書の中に
there is actually a complete volume.
完本1冊あるが
Unfortunately, it is my grandfather's treasure
残念ながら 祖父の貴重な品で
and cannot be lent out.
貸し出しはできない
A gentleman does not take what others love.
人の物を奪うのは 君子の行いではありません
It is natural for Old Mr. Gongsun
お祖父さんが貴重な品を惜しむのも
to cherish treasures.
納得できます
However...
しかし
Although it cannot be lent out,
貸し出しはできないとは言え
I can copy the fragment of the Go manual
棋譜の断簡を
and give it to you.
写して渡してもいい
Thank you, Headmaster.
ありがとうございます 学長
[Penetration and Subtlety]
[通幽達微]
A ruler
君主とは
should bear the responsibility of protecting the common people.
民を庇護する 責務を負うべきものです
Consort Dowager An,
安太妃様　拝啓
our new student An Xu
新入りの書生安旭は
is actually the Princess Royal in disguise.
実はお忍びの長公主様です
I have noticed this
臣下である私が気づき
and dare not keep it hidden.
隠し立てはできず
I report it for Your Highness's consideration.
ご報告いたします　どうかご明察を
[Yixiang Restaurant]
[溢香楼]
Qianqian?
浅姉さん
Where is she?
浅姉さんはどこ？
Changyu.
長玉
You scared me.
びっくりした
You asked me to come,
会いに来てって言ったのに
but you weren't here.
姿も見せなかったから
I was about to leave.
もう帰るところだったわ
Go sit down.
そっちに座って
Are you feeling better?
体はもう大丈夫？
I'm fine.
ええ 平気よ
You sent me medicine and food.
あなたが薬も食べ物も送って
I've even gained weight.
太っちゃったわ
How about you?
あなたは？
Were you scared that night?
あの晩は驚かされたの？
If you're afraid,
もし怖く思うなら
you can tell me.
私に言ってもいいわ
Don't bottle it up.
我慢すると病気になるよ
It was nothing.
平気よ
I've seen it all.
どんなことも経験してきたわよ
Just because a bad guy scared me with a stick,
悪党に棒で脅されたくらいで
does that mean I should be scared to death?
生きられなくなると思うの？
But your husband...
それよりあなたの旦那さん
He was quite scary that night.
あの晩は怖かったわ
He's not usually like that.
普段はあんな人じゃないの
He just can't stand anyone hurting me.
私が傷つけられて 黙っていられなかっただけよ
I know.
分かってるわ
You two love each other,
愛し合ってる夫婦だから
and it makes everyone jealous.
誰でもうらやましく思うわ
By the way,
そうだ
look at this.
これを見て
Times are chaotic now.
今世の中が混乱してるので
We must learn to protect ourselves.
自分の身に守るようにならないと
What is this?
これ…何？
Cornel water.
茱萸の汁よ
I got a bigger bottle this time.
今回は大きい瓶に入れたの
Last time it ran out at a critical moment.
前回は肝心な時に使い尽くしたから
This should be enough.
今回なら十分でしょ
If sprayed in the eyes, it causes swelling, pain,
目に入ると痛くて腫れる上に 3日間も目が見えなくなる
I didn't know cornel could be used like that.
茱萸にそんな使い方もあるわね
Is this what you used on Butcher Guo?
この前 郭豚屠りに使ったやつね
If that's the case,
じゃあ
garlic, ginger, and peppercorns could work too.
ニンニクや生姜 山椒でも このように使えるね
That Guo got off easy.
郭というやつには もったいないわ
Headmaster?
学長？
I remember someone playing Go with me
この前
from a distance in the Fengyu Pavilion.
雨の廊亭で誰かと顔合わずに 碁を打ち
Our moves went back and forth, breaking stalemates again and again.
何度も打ち合い 難局を解決したことを思い出した
Who is playing Go here?
ここで碁を打っているのは誰なの？
Looks like the game isn't over.
まだ終わっていないようだわ
I'll place it here.
ここに打ちましょう
Is that so?
そうですか
That was really a meeting of kindred spirits.
まさに精神の交流と言えますね
Another white piece was placed!
白子が移動されました
Look.
ご覧ください
Your Highness,
長公主様
I think someone is inviting you to play.
対局に誘われているようです
I'm the one who intruded on someone else's game.
私の方が他人の対局に 突き込んだのよ
I also have a friend
実は私にもある友人がいます
who is excellent at Go.
彼は碁の腕が立ってます
But...
しかし
we've never met.
一度も会ったことはありません
What a coincidence.
なんと奇遇だな
Go reveals a gentleman's virtue.
碁は君子の徳の表しです
Although I haven't seen my opponent,
私は相手に会ったことは ありませんが
I can glimpse his thoughts through the game.
盤面から相手の心を 伺うことができます
Playing remotely is like having a conversation.
顔合わない対局は会話と同じです
It's all about
求められるのは
that moment of connection.
心が通じ合うその瞬間です
How do I compare
では私と学長の友人と比べると
to your friend?
いかがです
Although we haven't met,
会ったことはありませんが
your Go skills are better than theirs.
あなたの方が上手だ
Once I get your "The Mystery of Qi",
学長の「気蘊玄機」を手に入れれば
my skills will improve even further.
私の腕がさらに上がるでしょう
Perhaps...
もしかして
I'll be able to meet him soon.
すぐにその方と 会えるかもしれません
In that case,
それならば
when you meet,
会う際には
you must play a game together.
ぜひ一局を打つものです
Young Master!
若様
Y-Young Master! Someone from home is here.
若…若様 実家の者が来ました
Home?
実家？
Your Highness.
長公主様
I have been ordered to ask you to return to the palace.
私めは勅命によりお戻り いただくようお迎えに上がりました
[Seeking Truth in the Classics]
[青簡尋真]
I don't know how the Consort Dowager learned
太妃娘娘がどこから お聞きになったかわかりませんが
that you swapped identities with Mr. An
公主様が安若様と身分を入れ替え
and came to study at Luyuan Academy.
麓原書院に 通っていることを知ってます
What did Mother say?
母上は何とおっしゃいましたか
Her Highness has confined Mr. An.
太妃娘娘は 安若様を閉じ込められました
She's furious about this.
娘娘はこの件でひどく怒られたため
She originally allowed you to return to the Capital next month,
本来なら公主様は来月まで都に お戻りになることを認めましたが
but now you'll have to return to the palace today.
本日中にお戻りになるよう 命じられました
Your Highness.
長公主様
I've had people seal the backyard.
私めは裏庭を封じらせましたので
No one will notice your departure.
お姿を誰にも見られません
The academy will claim An Xu withdrew for personal reasons.
安旭が事情により退学したと 書院が公表するようになり
This will save everyone's face.
皆の顔を立てます
You are thorough, Nanny.
ばあやの考えは行き届いてるね
I apologize for my incompetence.
私めの力不足です
Your Highness, please.
公主様 どうぞこちらへ
Master,
和尚様
for the past half month,
この半月間
have you been the one playing Go with me?
私と碁を打っていたのは あなたですか
I did not expect that
老僧も思いもよりませんでした
the one playing chess here every day
毎日ここで碁を打ってくれたのは
would be a lady.
まさか女子だったとは
Right.
そうですね
Those who can be in Guangling Temple every day
毎日この広陵寺にいるのは
could only be the monks of the temple.
寺の僧侶だけですね
I overthought it.
私の考えすぎでした
To play Go remotely in this pavilion
この廊亭で顔合わずに 碁を打ってたとは
implies a destined bond.
運命の絆と言えるでしょ
Gongsun, why sever this connection?
公孫さんはなぜその縁を 断ち切るのですか
I am but a carefree idler,
私はただのしがない閑人で
with nothing to my name.
無一文の身です
How could I dare to hold up such a lady?
あの方の将来を 台無しにはできません
It was fine when I didn't know she was a girl.
相手が女子とは 知らないならまだ続けますが
But now that I know,
知ってしまったからには
it would be improper to disturb her further.
これ以上ご迷惑はかけられません
I remember
この前
someone playing Go with me from a distance in the Fengyu Pavilion.
雨の廊亭で誰かと顔合わずに 碁を打ち
Our moves went back and forth,
何度も打ち合い
breaking stalemates again and again.
難局を解決したことを思い出した
I also have a friend
実は私にもある友人がいます
who is excellent at Go.
彼は碁の腕が立ってます
But...
しかし
we have never met.
一度も会ったことはありません
What a coincidence.
なんと奇遇だな
Perhaps...
もしかして
I'll be able to meet him soon.
すぐにその方と 会えるかもしれません
Please.
どうぞ
Do you know why I came back?
私が戻った理由が知ってるの？
The road ahead is long.
この先は長いですが
I only wish for Your Highness to return to the capital safely.
私はただ長公主様が無事に京に お戻りになることだけ願ってます
You knew my identity long ago?
私の正体をとっくに知っていたのね
I only found out your identity the day before yesterday.
正体は一昨日知りました
When you first arrived at the academy,
君が書院に来られた日
I noticed that you were a woman.
君が女子であることに 気づいておりました
Who is An Xu?
安旭は誰？
An Xu.
安旭
He's calling you.
呼ばれてるぞ
Mr. An.
安書生
You look so outstanding,
これほど優れた容姿で
♪ I just don't want to ♪
♪ 私はただ嫌だ ♪
magnificent,
凛々しくて
♪ Keep weighing every word ♪
♪ 言葉を練ることが ♪
♪ And hiding in time in silence ♪
♪ 時間が経っても 黙ってるのは ♪
and distinguished.
立ち居振る舞いも見事とはな
I just didn't expect
ただ思いもよりませんでした
♪ It's not that I don't believe in karma ♪
♪ 因果を信じなく ♪
that you were actually the current Princess Royal.
まさか当代の長公主様だったとはな
♪ That I'm being stubborn ♪
♪ 執着するわけではない ♪
♪ Some endings have long been ♪
♪ 多くの結果は ♪
I came to this academy for someone.
ある人のために この書院に来たのです
♪ Weathered through a thousand years ♪
♪ 千年間でになっていって ♪
♪ Traced by those who come after ♪
♪ 後世の者に描写された ♪
♪ Compared to fading away in sorrow ♪
♪ 憂鬱で亡くなるより ♪
♪ I'd rather fight ♪
♪ 思う存分にする方がマシさ ♪
♪ Life's bitterness ♪
♪ 世間の苦しみは ♪
♪ Comes from love ♪
♪ 感情が豊富であるためだ ♪
♪ Love, yet so hard to hold ♪
♪ 愛は得難い存在だ ♪
♪ Like holing a torch in the wilderness ♪
♪ 野原で灯を探すようだ ♪
That the Princess Royal favors our academy
書院が長公主様のお目に留まり
♪ Time sings a mournful song ♪
♪ 時間の悲歌とは ♪
is an honor for us all.
我々一同光栄の至りと 思っております
♪ Gathered little yet parted often ♪
♪ 集まり少なく 別れ多いことだ ♪
♪ Just as tears fall into the long river ♪
♪ 涙が川に落ちたばかりで ♪
This is the Go manual I copied for you as I promised,
これはこの前長公主様と 約束して写した棋譜
♪ I must dive into the starry stream ♪
♪ 星の空に身を投げる ♪
"The Mystery of Qi."
「気蘊玄機」です
♪ Don't mind me ♪
♪ 私のことを構わん ♪
♪ Everything has happened ♪
♪ 覆水盆に帰らなくても ♪
I'm giving it to you now
今は餞の記念として
♪ A thousand years from now no one's blood will remain warm ♪
♪ 千年後誰もこの世にいらず ♪
as a parting gift.
長公主様に送りましょう
♪ Let them laugh and mock ♪
♪ 他人に笑われても ♪
♪ I just want you to remember me ♪
♪ 私のことを覚えてもらう ♪
♪ Don't care about ♪
♪ 後世の評判も ♪
♪ Leaving a name in history ♪
♪ 構わん ♪
♪ I only want to leave a mark in your life ♪
♪ 君の命の中で 生きた跡を残せばいい ♪
♪ I will let go ♪
♪ 思い切って ♪
♪ After taking this one last gamble ♪
♪ 我儘にする ♪
♪ Don't mind ♪
♪ 構わん ♪
♪ The carved stones or constellations ♪
♪ 碑に刻まれた宿命 ♪
♪ I'll cast all karma behind me ♪
♪ 因果を全て忘れる ♪
♪ Playing war with the lords ♪
♪ 烽火で諸侯を欺くように ♪
♪ Leaving no trace of fate ♪
♪ 宿命と必死に戦うんだ ♪
Headmaster. Headmaster.
学長　学長
It is so late. Why are you still up?
夜更けに まだ起きてるのか
An asked me to pass this letter to you.
安兄からの手紙が 預かってます
So it was her.
まさか彼女だと
In this game of Go,
この盤面の勝負は
I was utterly crushed.
完膚なきまでに負けたようだな
[Composed]
[従容有致]
Your Highness.
太妃娘娘
Since Princess Royal returned from the river region,
長公主はここに戻ってきましたから
she has stayed behind closed doors
ずっと部屋に閉じこもってて
and barely touched her meals.
食事もしませんでした
It seems Gongsun Yin has no affection
どうやら公孫鄞も
for the Princess Royal.
長公主に関心がないようです
If she knows,
長公主がそれを知ったら
she would be heartbroken.
きっとひどく お傷つきになるでしょう
The Gongsun family even sent a personal letter,
公孫から直々に手紙が届き
sincere in their words.
言葉も実に丁寧で
I was a little surprised.
私は少々意外だったわ
But with Her Highness's temperament,
ただ長公主の性格から言えば
she probably won't give up easily.
簡単には諦めないでしょうね
Shu is still young
姝兒はまだ若イノで
[Consort Dowager An, Mother of Qi Shu]
[斉姝の母 安太妃]
and doesn't understand all the complexities.
複雑な事情が分かっていない
The Gongsun family may have prestige,
公孫家は名望があるけど
but after all, they are not a suitable match.
良縁の相手ではないわ
You are right, Your Highness.
太妃娘娘のおっしゃるとおりです
How should we persuade Her Highness?
長公主様の方は どう説得すればよいでしょう
Grand Tutor Li has a reputation for virtue in court.
李太傅は朝廷で賢名高い
His eldest grandson, Li Huai'an,
李家の長孫李懐安は
is said to have achieved much in the Northwest.
西北でかなりの功績を 上げているそうね
He's also a man of great appearance
見た目もなかなかのもので
and could be considered a suitable match.
良縁と言えるわ
Perhaps we should find a chance
時機を作って
and arrange a meeting between him and Shu.
姝兒に会わせてみよう
I'll make the arrangements immediately.
では すぐに手配いたします
Shu,
姝兒
don't blame me for being harsh.
母さんを薄情だと恨まないで
No matter how unwilling you are now,
あなたがどれだけ不満でも
you'll understand in the future.
いずれ分かる日が来るわ
[Three days later]
[三日後]
A blind date with the Princess Royal?
長公主様と見合うって？
It seems my grandfather
祖父は
is still obsessed with his rivalry against Wei Yan
まだ魏厳との対立関係にこだわり
and wants to help me secure a footing
私を早く皇族の中で
among the royal nobility.
地位を固めさせたいのだろう
In the end,
どうせ
it's just party disputes.
派閥争いにすぎない
It brings no benefit
国の安泰や
to the stability of the state
民衆の幸福には
or the welfare of the people.
何の役も立てない
My Lord.
大人
The Grand Tutor is your grandfather.
太傅は一応大人の祖父でもあります
You should try to persuade him.
どうかお諌めください
I may be short-sighted,
私は浅学ですが
but all these years at the border,
ここ数年辺境にいて
[To my grandson, Huai'an]
[吾孫懐安親展]
whether it was General He or the Marquis of Wu'an,
賀将軍も武安侯も
although they belong to the Wei faction,
魏派ではありますが
they were fearless in battle
死を恐れぬ勇敢で
and good men who defended the border.
辺境を守る立派な男です
Grandfather has given orders.
祖父の命令だから
I have no choice but to go back.
一度戻らねばならない
Fortunately,
幸いに
the Marquis of Wu'an is still alive.
武安侯はまだ生きている
As long as he is here,
彼がいる限り
the Northwest will remain stable.
西北が混乱になることはない
Dry weather!
空気が乾いています
[Tofu]
[豆腐]
Beware of fire!
火の用心
Lin'an is indeed a nice place.
林安は本当にいい所だな
If I can settle down one day,
いつか安定になれば
I'd also like to live such a
私もこんな
carefree life like a drifting cloud.
悠々自適な暮らしをしたいな
Did Lord Li really return to the Capital?
李大人は本当に京に戻ったのか
I met him on my way home.
帰り道で会ったの
He said now that the matter with Guo has been resolved,
郭というやつの事件は解決したから
he must go back to Lucheng to report first,
先に盧城へ戻って報告し
then go to the Capital.
それから京へ向かうって
What else did he say?
ほかには？
He asked when my parents arrived in Lin'an
両親がいつ林安に来たと
and if I remember what happened 16 years ago.
16年前のことを 覚えてるかと聞いた
I was only 2 then.
あの頃私はまだ二歳だったのよ
How could I remember that?
覚えているわけないじゃない
I need to ask my grandfather about that.
お爺さんに聞かないと
Changning, we have roasted chestnuts.
長寧 焼き栗よ
Changyu, Zheng, look who's back.
姉さん 義兄さん 誰が帰ってきたか見て
[Be a Good Person]
[いい人になれ]
Zheng didn't lie to me.
義兄さんは嘘をついてなかった
The falcon is really back.
隼隼が本当に帰ってきた
You're so good at taming birds?
鳥の調教がうまいのね
Maybe you just fed it too well,
うまいご馳走を与えすぎたから
so it couldn't bear to leave.
離れたくなくなった恐れもあるな
Is it that greedy?
そこまでの食いしん坊なの？
Since you know how to come home,
ちゃんと帰ってきたから
I won't lock you in the cage anymore.
もう籠には入れないわ
You can be free.
自由にしてあげるわ
It's just like me.
私に似てるね
Was it born of my mother too?
私と同じ母さんが産んだの？
Yes.
そうよ
Raising it also needs a lot of food.
どっちも食いしん坊だわ
Here.
ほら
The dream in the Fengyu Pavilion has ended.
雨の廊亭での夢が覚めた
Baffling.
訳が分からないな
Your Lordship,
侯爺
that rascal Li Huai'an has really left Lin'an.
李懐安のやつは 本当に林安を離れました
Mr. Gongsun's diversion tactic really worked.
公孫先生の調虎離山の計は 見事ですな
I'm also curious about
私も知りたいな
what tricks that brat used.
あいつがどんな手を使ったのか
By the way,
そうだ
at the border between Yanzhou and Chongzhou,
焉州と崇州の境で
bandits have been raiding military grain.
山賊が兵糧を奪ってました
Wei Xuan was furious this time
魏宣は激怒し
and ordered them to be wiped out within 10 days.
十日以内の掃討を命じました
What kind of bandits have a death wish
どんな山賊も
to repeatedly rob government grain convoys?
何度も役所の兵糧を奪う勇気がない
It must be Prince Changxin behind this.
きっと長信王が裏で 糸を引いているに違いありません
That fool Wei Xuan
魏宣というあの能なし
is about to fall into their trap.
もうすぐ罠にはまるだろ
Keep monitoring all recent intelligence
最近は兵糧に関する情報を
about the grain.
引き続き見張ってろ
Yes.
はっ
Your Lordship,
侯爺
it's late. You should head back and rest
夜も更けましたので お戻りください
before the Marchioness...
奥様に
be-becomes suspicious.
怪しまれないように
My stupid mouth ran faster than my brain.
このバカ口は考えるより先に
I blurted out my thoughts.
本音を漏らしてしまった
Let's go.
行くぞ
[Enjoy Yourself]
[食飲遊楽]
Manager.
店主さん
Manager Zhao from the Lin'an Rice Shop
林安米屋の趙店主が
booked a private room on the second floor
二階で個室を予約して
to entertain an important guest.
大事な客をもてなしてます
Look,
見て
he ordered our best wine and dishes.
うちの一番いい酒と料理を 注文しました
Okay, I got it.
分かったわ
Go get things ready.
準備を続けて
I'll go up to greet them in a moment.
すぐ挨拶に行く
Alright.
わかった
[Heaven-class]
[天字號]
Manager Zhao.
趙店主
Taking time out of your busy schedule to visit Yixiang Restaurant,
お忙しい中 我が溢香楼にお越しいただき
it's truly an honor for us.
光栄ですわ
[Zhao Xun, Manager of Lin'an Rice Shop]
[林安米屋店主 趙詢]
Manager Yu, you're too polite.
俞店主 ご丁寧にどうも
How is business today?
今日の商売はいかがだろ
Business is good, of course.
もちろんうまく行けますわ
May I ask who this guest is?
こちらのお客様は？
This is a rice merchant from the Capital,
京城から来た米商の
Mr. Qi.
斉若様だ
[Qi Min]
[斉旻]
He's here to discuss some business with me.
商談をしているところだ
So you are a distinguished guest from afar.
これはこれは 遠路はるばるお越しのお客様ですね
I hope the food and wine suit your tastes.
お料理はお口に合うのでしょうか
If you need anything,
何かご入用でしたら
please just let me know.
何なりとお申し付けくださいね
The food and wine are excellent.
お料理もお酒も実に素晴らしい
Especially this Snow Bun Soup.
特にこの雪霽羹馍汁は絶品です
This is our signature dish.
このお店の看板ですわ
To serve such an distinguished guest
お客様方にお仕えできるのは
is my honor.
私の光栄です
Let me propose a toast to you.
私からお二方へ一杯を
Let me know if you need anything else.
では何かご入用の際は またお呼びください
Manager Yu, please wait.
俞店主 お待ちを
Mr. Qi, you might not know,
斉若様はご存じないでしょうが
but I haven't been running a shop in Lin'an for long.
私が林安で店を開いてる時間は短い
But Manager Yu has been in business for years
でも俞店主の方は 長年ここで商売して
and knows the local network best.
人脈関係にも一番詳しい
If you have any business ideas,
若様が何か商売を されたいのでしたら
you could ask Manager Yu for advice.
俞店主にお聞きになるのが よろしいかと思ってます
What business are you planning, sir?
若様はどのような商売を なさりたいですか
I am not familiar with the rice trade.
米屋のことには 詳しくありませんが
But if you want to collaborate with someone,
どなたかと組みたいと お考えでしたら
I can introduce you to a few managers.
何人か店主をご紹介できますわ
Manager Yu, you are very experienced
俞店主は客あしらいがお上手で
in receiving guests.
なかなかのやり手だ
It seems you really do know a lot of people.
確かに顔が広いようだ
Our shop serves guests from all over.
当店には様々な お客様がいらっしゃいますので
We believe harmony brings wealth.
和気をもつこそ財が集まることを 重んじてます
In business,
商売ですから
it's always good to know more people.
顔が広いほうが都合がいいものです
It's all for business.
全ては商売のためだね
I understand.
納得できるぞ
Please enjoy yourselves.
ではお客様方 ごゆっくり
I will go attend to other guests.
私は他のお客様の応対を いたします
Please go ahead, Manager Yu.
俞店主 どうぞ